so that completes a section which I
didn't finish in Phoenix from from
before okay from up above why did I say
that because he's about to quote nard
okay AR
n who was brought to us by Master T okay
like I don't know to put it in 1960s
terms Master chity is Ed
Solomon and
uh and the guard is the Beatles okay all
right somebody asked me who the Beatles
were the other
day I felt really bad
okay uh so is where was
that
uh here he goes
this is one of those nagar junian uh
incomprehensible verses and I'll I'll
give it to you
incomprehensibly
uh if there if there were no
self that were not the part of Nick if
there were no Nick that were the parts
of
Nick did I get that
right
yeah
sorry there's no Nick who is exclusive
of of his Parts how's that there's no
Nick which is exclusive on this Parts in
tibetan the word Parts here is nmba
nemba means that which was taken
on and it always refers to the parts
that you took on when you were born your
body and mind that you assumed when you
were born okay so if there were no body
and mind which Nick assumed upon his
birth
uh then there let's say let's say
there's no Nick which is which is
separate from the parts he took on when
he was born okay let's say there is no
such thing
n
uh then then then the the guy would have
to be his Parts all right then the guy
would have to be the parts he took
on uh if it's true that he is just the
parts he took on then he's not
Nick because Nick's the whole thing
right
okay okay here we
go now he's going to try to clarify okay
you took on a certain body and mind when
you were
[Music]
born is there a person who took the
M no it's a question that the word for
your body and mind in tibetan and in
Sanskrit is that which was taken on at
your birth but who took them
on
okay all right see I took a Reaper right
who who took who you are the
reaper okay I took on Parts when I was
born I took on a body and mind when I
was born what do you mean I you were the
body of mind you are the body of mind
okay then it's we
[Laughter]
you see there's no they're just trying
to point out that there's a there's a
fundamental mistake in how we think and
by the way I like to I like to say
although people don't like to hear it
it's reflected in the use of language
itself uh our languages are defective
you can't express in our languages any
language in the world you can't
express truth because those those
languages are a reflection of a mind
which was always making a mistake those
languages themselves are mistaken the
use of you and me is a m is a is a
contradiction there's no such thing as
you and me but we have those words and
and we can't actually think or express
ourselves differently it's very
difficult when your words themselves are
defective your language is
defective but that's another story
okay not only that jup what's
jupa there's two famous
jupas umala jupa and Chalan jupa so
which one would he's probably talking
about here yeah the okay majar
maatar entering the middleway written
by Master T okay so he's quot he's right
away he's jumping to
master so you can think of our whole
emptiness lineage as as
Buddha okay
it would be a contradiction to say that
Nick had taken on
Nick okay it would be a contradiction to
say that Nick had taken on Nick at his
birth if that were the
case then the then the agent of an
action and the action itself or the
agent of an action and the object of
that action would be the same
person okay right
the The Taker and what was taken would
be the same person and that's a
contradiction you can't take you can't
reach out and take yourself because
you're the
reacher okay it's not possible
[Music]
okay Nick what he's basically saying is
that if Nick were the sum of his Parts
okay if he were just
one
okay if we could see Nick without
checking out his Parts you see if he
were just one
then uh would become the same
thing the one who took his birth and the
birth that was taken would be the
same which is a contradiction you has to
be a taker before you have to take
something that he took
okay it can't it has one has to preed
the other okay
and uh the body and the one who
possesses the body would have to be the
same thing right Nick's body and Nick
would have to be the same thing but then
you couldn't say Nick because Nick means
he's different from the body you know
John's book Ben's pen you know they're
different stuff that's why Ben can have
a pen cuz not the pen okay so the minute
you say Nick's body it means Nick is
different from his body but Nick's not
different from his body because you took
away the body wouldn't have a Nick okay
uhin the one the the limbs of the body
in tobet they consider five which
are arms legs and head okay uh and the
person who possesses those limbs okay
can you say my head my arm my feet you
say right then but are you separated
from
those you're not separate from that so
basically when you say my head you're
saying head's head or you're saying my
my and they're both crazy okay and it's
not just a game okay we're not just
playing a game it's not just what do you
call
sophistry it's not just it's not just
like word game
it's
that your your your perceptions are
screwy and it's reflected in the the
words you're using your all of your
languages on your planet okay you say
Nick's body but Nick can't exist without
the body Nick has to be in a sense the
body and so he can't be you can't say
body's body and you can't say Nick's
Nick because then they'd be separate and
Nick isn't separate from Nick Nick is
just one Nick's not plural we already
said that
okay if your language is screwy that
means your thinking is screwy okay and
that's why aspin doesn't work on your
planet
okay so suppose I suppose Nick is his
body all right then uh now we got to juk
but the same Tex Master time's text
says that's that's not a big deal
um are Nick's Parts Nick is Nick's leg
Nick can you have a Nick without legs
arms and head I mean technically I guess
you could but there was that that movie
but
uh now you're going to spend all night
trying to figure out which
movie can't have a Nick without the
basic parts of a Nick
okay but if Nick is his basic parts then
make then there's lots of Nicks because
there's lots of
Parts if Nick is his body and mind then
he's already two there's already two
Nicks going on if he's not his body and
mind then where else is he
okay there's just a basic fundamental
problem with
everything there are five parts to the
classical parts to a person and then
there would have to be five mix because
if he's his Parts if Nick is his Parts
if he's not his parts then what is he is
somebody else's Parts okay
if you go the opposite way okay if you
say look uh Nick's not plural Nick's not
five Nicks there's or two Nicks there's
only one Nick well then he should only
have one
part because that's who Nick is
okay you're you're screwed up either way
if you say Nick is all his parts then
he's there's five Nicks running around
if you say no no no Nick is only one
well then he only has one part
but he doesn't only have one part
because he got at least body and mind
that's
two got
it if it's confusing you got
it
okay so he's listing problems with with
with what it would be to say there's a
Nick who owns his Parts his body and
mind if you say there's a nick who owns
his body and mind if you say there's a
Nick who took on a body and mind when he
was born which is to say there's a
separate Nick from his body and mind
because he had to be there already to
take them on okay then there's all these
problems pop up he's just listing
problems randomly okay here's another
problem
uh then it would have been
meaningless uh to come into your
mother's
womb cuz he was already
if Nick took on a body and mind when he
was
born then there's no reason for the body
and mind to develop in the mother's womb
because Nick took them on so there must
have been enough to Nick already without
the body and mind that was produced in
the
womb okay all
right young are we are we out of
time we still have a few minutes okay uh
by the way I was late because I was
doing some service for my teacher and
and that's the way it should be okay
that's most important we did do you
remember Connecticut who was there they
bought a
tent they they put all the chairs out
they a couple hundred people were coming
and then my llama gave me a job that
weekend said you have to do it this
weekend and I just canceled it there and
there were like a couple hundred people
sitting there in the waiting you know so
you're lucky all right
uh I never went
um then there was
the the backline that was pretty funny
okay the lady who paid for the pen T
took me into a room and uh that was a
long story but uh she was quite big and
she she took me into the room and
slammed the door and then all my
students were waiting and then she sat
down on the couch but she fell off cuz
she sat she was so mad she missed the
couch and then uh you know who and then
there was a huge crash and they thought
that she had thrown me through the
window and they all rushed in you know
and she sprawled on the
ground okay anyway these are passing
into
myth it's true
that
[Music]
was
so uh if I if Nick is his body okay if
he is his body if okay if Nick is his
body then you know when a person dies uh
you burn the body right and the body
becomes basma it becomes powder and
then in that case I would also have to
become powder Nick would also have to be
Nick would become
powder the Nick who took birth and took
on the body would also be pulverized
okay but but you don't say that you
don't say we burned the body and Nick
got
pulverized okay all right here I say not
only that not
who takes rebirth I mean let's take it
from the other Ang let's take it from
the death you know going
on uh who who crosses Over N those of
you who are want to become translators
okay n j a very weird phrase means who
crosses
over so who is it that crosses over
did you ever think about it I mean how
much crosses
over because that must be the real you
in a way right who crosses over if you
if Nick is his body and mind there's no
one to cross over because the body and
mind were left
behind Okay who crosses over
okay say
if Nick were his body okay we're still
trying to figure this
out is he his body or is he the
possessor of his body is neither one
works if he's his body all these
problems pops up pop up if he's not his
body then who the hell is he I mean
where is he okay all right because he
can't be there right out his
body here we go so if it if you were
your body then when you died
well who who takes the next birth who
who who crosses
over who's the body is destroyed the
body is gone if Nick is his body then
where's Nick after he died who who
crosses on to the next birad because the
body's left
behind and then you know this is not
compelling arguments to to people who
grew up in a culture that doesn't
believe in rebirth anyway okay uh but
that's another story
in that case since the body can't cross
over then neither could
okay all
right and if Nick is his
body then is it the case that there are
no beings who don't have
bodies and and we posit people who live
in the formless realm okay we say there
are people who are almost body lless
they're just minds they're just what do
you call it disconnected Minds there are
places where people live just as mental
they have very subtle uh pra bodies but
basically they are not physical they are
just
Consciousness they are just beings of
Consciousness they don't have a physical
body and they don't live in a physical
place so if Nick were his body then he
couldn't take birth there because there
wouldn't be anything left okay but you
don't believe all that anyway doc pimo
May
dark
pble there would also be the problem of
saying that Nick were found Nick were
made of
atoms bble means molecular
substance stuff that is made of
molecules or atoms is Nick made of
atoms is is Nick made of you can go like
this or you can go like
this it's you're doing pretty good for
having cold and all that not so many
colds as as earlier
uh could Nick be molecular
matter no because he has to possess that
matter it's Nick's body Nick is separate
from the body or you couldn't say Nick's
body okay are you are you telling me
he's not separate from the
body is he separate from his body or not
if he's not you can't say Nick's
body if he is then then you're running
around saying body's body or Nick's
Nick okay either way it's a problem
right
okay
uh so he just covered the problems of
saying that Nick is his body now let's
see what happens if you say Nick is his
mind
what's cap and how does it different
from
cap I'll tell you another funny story I
like this story I was in Tu his a
teaching and he has this a friend of
mine he has an Oxford translator a
friend of
mine an old DE an old debate uh partner
and uh so he was transcending for him
and his Holiness was talking about
patience you know and his and so
somebody asked a question you know
someone keeps bugging me over and over
again you know what should I do and it's
hus is like you know go to them once and
say ask them not to do that you know and
then if they keep doing it then go to
them again and ask them politely not to
do it you know and then uh if they keep
doing it you know like be a little more
forceful and try to make it clear to
them that you don't want to do it and
then if they keep doing it tell them to
C which means eat
and then the translator was
like and he's in front of like 5,000
people you know and he and he goes
through the whole thing you know and I'm
waiting for the
end and his hoess is waiting for the end
and uh and he gets to the end and he
says express your extreme displeasure
[Laughter]
so anyway this is not that Kaka this
isak Kaka which means uh ice or to feel
cold to people who don't learn tobet and
carefully get into problems you ask for
a glass of water with ice but you say
the wrong
word you can get all didn't this would
be a good place with all those stopped
up toilets
okay uh
anyway
uh if
the if the if Nick's mind were Nick then
Nick could never say I'm cold or I'm
hungry okay because that can only only
the body can feel cold or
hungry not the mind
and if you got cold or hot or if you got
hungry or thirsty Etc it would become
wrong to say I I'm I feel cold or I feel
hungry okay because those are only
detectable through the bodily senses if
if if Nick was limited to being his
mind uh then there's those problems he
couldn't say I I feel cold because the
mind cannot detect cold without the body
all
right so look we just gone through
demonstrating that Nick is not Nick's
body alone and then we went to proving
that Nick is not Nick's mind alone so
what would be the next thing to
disprove yeah Nick is not the
combination of the which is the more
difficult one okay here we go
uh if you are your body and mind
together then what sense would it make
to ever say my body or my
mind because then you're positing a
person who's separate from them okay if
you are the Comm of your body and mind
which is which you are
almost uh it would be illogical to say
my body and my mind because then you
would say the the body of the body and
mind and the mind of the body and mind
okay it wouldn't make
sense you almost are your body and mind
together but one more thing has to
happen which is yeah there has to be a a
seat in your mind which forces you to
see it that way
okay Shen
we we'll do just a few minutes
okay you do the you do
the and the block got
broken uh
moreover if if I were my parts okay if I
were my parts
then if I were one
thing
um if I were the Nick who had the parts
okay because that's what we think right
we say Nick's body and Nick's mind so we
think there's a Nick who's not the body
and not the mind he's the possessor of
the body and the mind okay if I were
that then uh I would always have to be
one in all times in all
places and in all ways then what does
that mean he
quotes again
[Music]
this
is if if Nick's parts were
Nick then it it would also have to come
in and out of
existence who's
it Nick okay if Nick is the parts of
Nick if Nick is his body and mind then
Nick also would have to come in and out
of existence
there's a couple ways to read this I'll
tell you one and you can go to bed
okay
uh the definition of a changing thing is
that it goes through continual cycles of
instantaneous destruction and and and
and Recreation okay all all of all all
of all things that are changing all the
things basically around you are are
going in and out of existence in a in an
instantaneous stream okay
that they last for a second some texts
say they don't even last they're there
for a second they come into being in a
millisecond they last for a millisecond
they go out of being in a millisecond
because they are results of carnic seeds
seeds pop open the seeds die the thing
stops and then there's another seed that
pops open so you are a you are a series
of
Stills okay you're you over 50 years 60
years are a series of Stills you are
frames in a
movie and each frame comes and each
frame goes all things are like that okay
all things are like that because they're
coming from seeds and the seeds only
last for a moment for a millisecond and
they they those frames fly by at 65 per
second and then we were talking about I
don't know to get video to work on a on
YouTube without looking jerky it has to
be about that so your life is your life
is Flowing at exactly the right speed
for you to think there is a time going
on
okay it's just a bunch of
Stills seeds going off and you're having
discreet impression at the rate of 65 a
second and they give you the they give
you the what the
word the impression but there's a better
one
anyway the illusion they give you the
illusion of your life going on and
passing through time okay because there
are seats coming you are getting
actually it's only still photographs
being laid in front of you uh at the
speed of 65 a second they is it Jason 65
just yeah it's around that not to look
jerky
100 okay IMX 65 second anyway that's
good enough he he does that for a living
okay so it happens to be that the Mind
throws up discreet pictures at the rate
of 65 a second and that gives you the
illusion of time passing and of the
world moving okay but it's not the world
moving mov it's just discreet pictures
being thrown up in front of your mind at
65 a
second that's what your body consists of
and that's what your mind consists of
Nick's body and Nick's mind are
just photos of the you know his body is
like this no really and
it's you see but 65 it's even like
you see and then it gives you the
illusion of movement but but in truth
those uh each each still is coming in
and out of existence okay each still
each frame is coming in and out of
existence therefore Ergo if Nick were
his body Nick would be coming in and out
of existence constantly that's all
that's all if Nick were only his body
if there were no Nick beyond the body
and mind who owned the body and mind
there's all those problems right but one
of the problems is that if Nick was his
body and mind Nick would be here and
gone 65 times every second and we know
it's only 65 times every minute when the
room is warm and he's tired okay like
he's in and
out okay I'm just having fun okay
uh all right it's not the case that he
disappears every 65th of a second right
if he were only his body then he would
Nick would be in and out every 65th of a
second okay all right maybe we should
stop
there uh this is hard okay that's why I
read you that little paragraph up above
that said you
know if you really want to get to the
bottom of the stuff you got a crack some
Kaa and it's not going to happen on the
first time you hear it okay you can boil
it down
to in practice right I think it's
important to do an in practice in
practice you have to boil it down to
recognize the Nick that's not there and
I think it's easier easiest to talk
about the Nick who's not who fault who's
not at fault that he was blamed for
stealing the books in the Centennial
room okay right the Nick who's not at
fault uh who was blame blamed for who
was accused of stealing books okay the
Nick who
didn't who wasn't that fault when he was
accused of stealing books that Nick what
never existed doesn't exist couldn't
exist there's no such thing all right
just just stay there that's enough okay
that's a practical
emptiness why because the next time you
get accused of something you didn't do
or criticized
by anyone who doesn't realize you're
perfect um then
uh then you won't get so upset okay
because because the the person they're
accusing doesn't
exist the person who was wrongly accused
doesn't exist so you don't have to get
upset about it because he's not there
you don't have to defend somebody who's
not
there then you save a lot of time and we
wear and terar on your body and mind
okay this whole thing of trying to
defend a Nick who's not there consumes
most of your life so if you could get
over that you might find other
interests
okay like golden rooms
[Music]
in
spe
[Music]
okay hang in there you're doing good